## Contact

Website GitHub jsbangsund.github.io @jsbangsund

## Skills

**Techniques -** Ellipsometry, atomic force microscopy, X-ray diffraction, electronic device characterization, UV-Vis spectroscopy, transient fluorescence, optical microscopy, physical vapor deposition

**Equipment -** lock-in amplifier, pulse generator, oscilloscope, source measure unit, spectrometer, pulsed and CW lasers, Arduino, cryostat

Programming - Python, MATLAB, LabView, GUI development, National Instruments VISA, Git, MongoDB, Image Processing, Optical modeling

# Leadership and Outreach

#### **Research Mentor**

UMN and MSU | 2014 - Present

Mentored three graduate students and seven undergraduates, leading to work in five publications

## **Science Fair Mentor**

Minnesota Academy of Science Bdote Middle School | Fall 2018

## **Workshop Volunteer**

Minnesota Tool Library May 2017 - Present

# **Student Chapter President**

Engineers Without Borders, MSU May 2014 - May 2015

# **John Bangsund**

# Optical and Electronic Materials Scientist

## **About**

I am an optical and electronic materials scientist with eight years of laboratory experience in photovoltaics and LEDs. I develop scientific software and hardware which enable new measurement techniques and improved data analysis. During my PhD work, I have applied these new techniques to better understand degradation mechanisms and excited state kinetics in organic LEDs.

## Education

## **University of Minnesota**

Ph.D. Materials Science | GPA: 3.9 | Expected Summer 2020 National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship (2015-2020) UMN College of Science and Engineering Fellowship (2015-2020)

# **Michigan State University**

B.S. in Materials Science & Engineering | GPA: 4.0 | May 2015 Concentration in Polymer Science, B.A. in Humanities, Minor in Spanish Goldwater Scholarship (2014), Alumni Distinguished Scholarship (2011-2015)

## **Work Experience**

## **Graduate Research Fellow**

University of Minnesota | Advised by Prof. Russell Holmes | Nov. 2015 - Present

- Collaborated with DuPont to characterize OLED degradation and explain stability differences between proprietary host materials
- Developed techniques based on optical probes to quantify the pathways of OLED degradation, such as changes in quantum yield and excited state kinetics
- Designed hardware and software for automation of OLED lifetime testing
- Helped build and maintain database for test data storage and analysis
- Combined AFM and optical microscopy with image analysis techniques to study crystallization and pattern formation in organic thin films
- Managed maintenance on vacuum equipment and gloveboxes
- Wrote open-source Python programs for test automation, OLED light outcoupling efficiency modeling, and crystal growth rate measurements

## **Undergraduate Research Assistant**

Michigan State University | Advised by Prof. Richard Lunt | Aug. 2012 - July 2015

- Initiated and led a project on near-infrared absorbers for organic photovoltaics which resulted in a licensed patent and three journal publications.
- Fabricated devices with solution processing and thermal evaporation
- Measured power conversion and external quantum efficiencies
- Discovered that anions can shift frontier energy levels, improving open-circuit voltage of small bandgap OPVs

# **Ellipsometry Technician**

UMN Characterization Facility | Minneapolis, MN | Oct. 2016 - Present Maintained instrument, trained new users, and analyzed samples for industry

## **Teaching Experience**

- Discussion Instructor, Introduction to Materials Science, University of Minnesota, Fall 2018 (Outstanding TA Award)
- Lead Teaching Assistant, Materials Properties Lab, University of Minnesota, Spring 2018 (Outstanding TA Award)
- Teaching Assistant, Thermodynamics of Materials, University of Minnesota, Fall 2016

## **Publications**

- 11 **JS Bangsund**, et al. Exciton Quenching Below Turn-on in Organic Light-Emitting Devices Due to Spontaneous Orientation Polarization. *In prep*.
- 10 D Rai, **JS Bangsund**, *et al.* Influence of Molecular Structure on Singlet and Triplet Exciton Diffusion in Phenanthroline Derivatives. *In prep.*
- 9 **JS Bangsund**\*, R Newcomb\*, *et al.* Role of Excimer Formation in Degradation of Organic Light-Emitting Devices. *Accepted. Applied Physics Letters* (2019). \*Equal contributors
- 8 **JS Bangsund** and Russell J. Holmes. Impacts of Degradation on Annihilation and Efficiency Roll-Off in Organic Light-Emitting Devices. *Proc. of SPIE.* (2019). DOI: 10.1117/12.2528780
- 7 **JS Bangsund**, et al. Spontaneous Formation of Aligned, Periodic Patterns During Crystallization of Organic Semiconductor Thin Films. *Nature Materials* (2019). DOI: 10.1038/s41563-019-0379-3
- 6 **JS Bangsund**\*, KW Hershey\*, *et al.* Improved Stability in Organic Light-Emitting Devices by Mixing Ambipolar and Wide Energy Gap Hosts. *Journal of the Society for Information Display* (2019). DOI: 10.1002/jsid.761. \*Equal contributors
- 5 **JS Bangsund**, et al. Isolating Degradation Mechanisms in Mixed Emissive Layer Organic Light-Emitting Devices. *ACS Applied Materials and Interfaces* (2018). DOI: 10.1021/acsami.7b16643
- 4 KW Hershey, **JS Bangsund**, et al. Decoupling Degradation in Exciton Formation and Recombination During Lifetime Testing of Organic Light-Emitting Devices. *Applied Physics Letters* (2017). DOI: 10.1063/1.4993618
- 3 CJ Traverse, M Young, **JS Bangsund**, *et al.* Anions for Near-Infrared Selective Organic Salt Photovoltaics. *Scientific Reports* (2017). DOI: 10.1038/s41598-017-16539-3
- 2 M Young, **JS Bangsund**, et al. Organic Heptamethine Salts for Photovoltaics and Detectors with Near-Infrared Photoresponse up to 1600 nm. *Advanced Optical Materials* (2016). DOI: 10.1002/adom.201600102
- 1 **JS Bangsund**, et al. Organic Salts as a Route to Energy Level Control in Low Bandgap, High Open-Circuit Voltage Organic and Transparent Solar Cells that Approach the Excitonic Voltage Limit. Adv. En. Mat. (2016). DOI: 10.1002/aenm.201501659

## **Conference Presentations**

- 5 **JS Bangsund**, et al. Impacts of Degradation on Annihilation and Efficiency Roll-off in Organic Light-Emitting Devices. Oral Presentation. SPIE Organic Electronics + Photonics, San Diego, CA. 08/2019.
- 4 **JS Bangsund**, et al. Spontaneous Formation of Aligned, Periodic Patterns During Crystallization of Organic Semiconductor Thin Films. Poster Presentation. Materials Research Society Fall Meeting, Boston, MA. 11/2018.
- 3 **JS Bangsund**, *et al.* Quantifying Multiple Active Degradation Mechanisms in Mixed Host Organic Light-Emitting Devices. Oral Presentation. Materials Research Society Spring Meeting, Phoenix, AZ. 4/2018.
- 2 **JS Bangsund**, et al. Understanding Improved Lifetime in Mixed Emissive Layer Organic Light-Emitting Devices. Oral Presentation. Optical Society of America Solid-State Lighting Meeting, Boulder, CO. 11/2017.
- 1 **JS Bangsund**, et al. Energy Level Control in Organic Salts for Efficient, Deep Near-Infrared Organic and Transparent Photovoltaics. Oral Presentation. Materials Research Society Spring Meeting, Phoenix, AZ. 3/2016.

#### **Patents**

■ RR Lunt, **JS Bangsund**, M Young, and CJ Traverse. *ORGANIC SALTS FOR HIGH VOLTAGE ORGANIC AND TRANSPARENT SOLAR CELLS*. PCT/US2016/026169. April, 2016. *Licensed by Ubiquitous Energy*.

## Interests